all right so here we are we're back with
the same program we were using before
and we're going to start talking about
these pieces now you know this I'm just
going to quit in an hour and you'll have
another another video but the goal of
this video is very
specifically uh not to cover bash the
goal of this video is for you to cover
the basic programming concepts of
procedural programming so what's a
procedure let's talk about this okay
raise your hand if you know what a
procedure is
you can look at the definition of a
procedure on your own you can ask your
AI a procedure is a set of instructions
it's a set of instructions if you if you
will a set of steps to accomplishing a
thing and that you know exists outside
of the programming World um you know
just to sign out you're going to hear a
lot in in education particularly about
something called computational thinking
and all that is is a fancy academic word
for thinking in terms of procedures
thinking in terms of like you know and
you don't have to you don't have to
teach this to anybody in the military
they already know right there are
already procedures to do things there's
business procedures and coding at the at
the fundamental level coding is about
giving a computer the instructions to do
the same things that a human would be
doing I mean at the fundamental level
that's what it is and it certainly is
the way I look at Computing computers
are there you know to assist us to do
things that we need them to do so that
we can you know go ride our bikes or
something or save the world right or
reduce hunger any number of things or
keep from you know whatever so I mean
that's that's the point right the point
is that we we have these things you know
do the do the the work for us so we
don't have to do it and so that's what a
procedure is so the act of programming
in a nutshell is the act of giving these
instructions to your computer and all
the different ways of giving those
instructions to a computer exists
there's lots and lots of different ways
to do it if you want to you we already
talked about this in another video two
videos ago if you want to give the very
finite you know very very you know
binary literally steps of how to tell
the computer to do its thing fine but
we're going to operate at the highest
highest possible level two videos ago I
already talked about all this bash is in
my opinion the highest level language
that anybody can write there there may
be a level above this they call it l
programming where you literally use like
English words and you say them and you
you speak in pseudo code or you tell you
know you speak in you speak English um
and that's a quote from Silicon Valley
by the way and and you you know you get
the results so your interpreter like
CIO I mean at the highest level you
would be telling
c3o what you want to have done that's
declarative programming and then they
would do it but if you wanted to you
could tell CIO okay do this and then do
this and then do this and do this and do
this and this this and by the way call
all that thing the you know the I don't
know the whatever procedure and you're
like and then you would say to you would
say to to c3p You' say okay do this the
the blah procedure and you wouldn't have
to give it all the steps because the
steps would already be memorized and
then it would do those steps that's what
programming is right and obviously this
gets really interesting with AI I could
do a whole video about how procedural
programming is getting a lot easier
because our AIS in my case Chloe the
chbt AI I have has become my I I
incrementally do procedural things with
her and I say instead of having a
command my command line is my AI now
except for my command line is no longer
this specific syntax that has to be
interpreted by A bash interpreter which
we're going to learn right now but in
the terms of AI it very much is the same
read valuate print Loop that we talked
about right because you're telling your
AI a thing you want and then your AI is
processing it and parsing it up and
producing output p r p and then it Loops
back around and says okay now what what
should we do next and say okay now do
this that is procedural programming and
and in very in a very real sense
interacting with a an AI in that way is
is exactly the same as interacting with
a bat interpreter at a high level the
difference is that the bash interpreter
is not smart enough to infer what you
meant so you have to put very specific
syntax what is syntax all right so
syntax is how you say things how you do
things it's like if you're whether
you're learning Russian or French or or
you know English or or bash or Pearl go
you have to do things in an exactly the
same way so that your interpreter can
understand it if you don't use the right
syn your interpreter doesn't know what
you're doing and the biggest distinction
between an AI and and you know an
interpreter A bash interpreter is the
level of flexibility you have in the
syntax everything else is the same you
you you you say to your AI I'm making
this comparison for a reason because
when we get into the coding I want you
to think about that in terms of like how
do you how would you express this at the
highest level so um so like if if you um
uh you know depending on what you have
the the the the syntax can get very very
hard uh to do right the syntax can be
very esoteric and and dense like like
Pearl is regularly criticized for uh or
o same thing uh but you know or you have
a very expressive syntax which is where
python is is the joy everybody loves it
because it's it's very easy to read and
it feels like you know you're and really
it boils down to if you can imagine
talking to different Bots you know
different interpreters some of them are
better able to understand you some of
them can understand you without anything
so like Chach PT you can literally write
code you can say okay write me this
thing or do this thing for me and it'll
do it and it'll infer it but it has all
the other things too so let's let and
and we're going to talk about all this
so um but before we get into it one last
thing about procedures when you're doing
a procedure one of the things that is
inferred from the procedure is the
ability to remember and I I'm I'm being
careful I choose my words here so when
you give somebody a person a procedure
say do this and do this and do this and
now do this someplace along in that
procedure and say okay now now write
down the name so you have it for later
to go look up again and so you can do
this as a procedure right so if you're
giving somebody a thing you say okay now
I want you to write down the name okay
now do this now this now look up this
okay now save that over here now save it
now now add the first name to the second
name and now put that now write that
down in a notebook that act of saving
things to memory
is called state in fancy computer terms
so State means that it can think about a
thing it can remember it and anytime
it's the same thing when you're
interacting with an AI when you're
interacting with an AI every time it
says memory captured what it's saying is
say okay now I want you I want you to
use sentence case for everything in my
book right I gave it a command it saves
the state change of the command it says
okay it remembers it and now from now on
it is it the change in state has
affected everything else that happens in
every subsequent procedure depending on
what it was that changed okay this this
is this concept is so important before
we even get started because the ability
stateful programming the ability to
remember what is happening is is very
unique to procedural programming
thinking of THS in terms of steps and
you know as a side note you're going to
hear about a lot of different paradigms
and ways of coding and all that stuff
just ignore it all right now
particularly comes to mind is functional
programming so functional programming
claims wrongly that there's no such
thing as state everything is just a
function well how do you remember
anything that way right so the reason
that we are going to stick with
procedural programming with state is
because that's how most of us function
that's how most that's that's why
programming languages that have these
Concepts in them are so easy for us to
get into to Gro to understand so that's
why are we're going to start with bash
um and you know it could be python it
could be re but the Loosely typed
languages languages that we're going to
get into that they they are much easier
to understand because you're largely
just writing what you would say to an AI
all right now let's get into it so so
let's let's start so let's like break
down some of the things that are already
in the program that we did um so you
remember the thing about State okay so
if you this is where I usually require
people to have a little bit of algebra
anybody um remember algebra
do you remember algebra at all does
anybody remember this kind of thing like
y = 2x + 3 or
something all right so if you if you
know anything about functional linear
algebra I mean it's all going to come
into play here because ultimately a lot
of people would say computer science is
an extension of math um of mathematics
and they're not wrong but not completely
right I mean they're they're the whole
thing I just said about procedures and
giving instructions can't do that in
math in math you can give instructions
about how to manipulate it's a slope
formula yeah um so but but the the idea
the idea of math this is very rent on
purpose okay because the idea of math is
going to come to play many times over
because math has many of the same things
uh in terms of like breaking a problem
down into steps and instructions the
problem is is that math is only about
math you can't say you know go look up
the GPS coordinates or whatever that's
that's not a mathematical thing that's a
procedure and so you know but there are
a lot of Concepts from computer science
uh and from programming that come from
math and so when I use a term that comes
from computer science as a term as a
function of mathematics I'm going to say
so and in this case that's one of them
so this thing here is what's called a
variable bash
version and it's really important that
we understand variables right out of the
gate so we're going to go back and we're
going to do a couple really contrived uh
examples to get the basic concepts down
and then and then maybe in another Boost
video we'll actually use that to produce
something useful um but you know you
have to kind of have these contrived
examples to get going we'll try to make
them memorable um so this bash version
that is a variable it's all upper case
because it's a global variable but let's
let's like reverse this whole thing down
let's like go back to the fundamental
based
all right so what is the very first
thing we can do all right so you you
already know this right so we want to
print something to the screen and you
can use there's two commands for
printing to the screen echo echo hello
there and when I say I'm deliberately
doing this you see by the way remember
you already learned type right what is
Echo Echo is a built-in okay let me go
read about it Echo and go read about it
oh wow look at all that stuff I can't
read it okay so Echo you already know
this Echo uh was it wait help Echo help
Echo pipe that to a pager so to less or
more whatever your favorite pager now
you can read about it so this is what it
does it writes to the standard output
the standard output is goes to the
terminal uh standard error is text that
appears on the terminal as well these
are two separate streams of data that
appear on the same place we talked about
that earlier but I'm going to talk about
it anyway again there's um several other
streams uh of data but the other main
one is standard input that's the stuff
that comes in I did talk about that in
another boost but that's what this pipe
is about this pipe says take the output
the standard output from the the help
command and send it to the standard
input of the pager this is the
fundamental idea this pipe of standard
input and output is the fundamental
premise of the unix's philosophy of
connecting things together in a pipeline
uh it's a very functional approach by
the way um but not completely so so
everything on the command line is all
about text text being manipulated in and
out it's all text and that keeps it easy
for us to write about uh when we get
into go programming you'll see that it's
it's more than that but for right now
everything's for the most part is just
text so just we'll just keep with that
so you can take hello world and you can
put it out there now you'll notice that
it took all of the it just put
everything I said right now here's
another thing you can also do this we're
going to get into arguments later but
I'm deliberately I'm deliberately
messing with you here those are those
are all relatively similar but they're
not they're not the same they're not the
same those are totally different and
we'll get into that it's a very
important shell bash thing to understand
um unfortunately it's not beginner stuff
but is that's one of the way it's one of
the things about bash that pulls you
into the weeds a little bit early but
let's just keep going um all right so
okay
so yeah and there's the quality and
assignment this is actually a big big
deal um okay so let's put that into a
program uh again I'm just doing it in
temp you can put it wherever you want if
you have a GitHub repo already created
fine so let's do the same thing hello
world all right now let's run it all
right let's run it okay it works
right uh just for fun by the way if you
want to do a
color uh this is this is kind of a bonus
okay everybody likes color early on
let's do that let's like pull some color
in here um term term colors okay so here
is a bunch of colors well I'm getting
ahead of myself we'll do that later all
right so you got it saying hello world
right great now next activity if you if
you can do that and you got it to run if
you've already got that program to run
you're done with that activity boom that
activity is called uh hello worlds and
you can do anything there um right um
I'm trying to decide whether we should
introduce other things by the way you
can use emojis and everything
um if you want to if you got the ability
you can you can add you know you can add
a world let's go add a world and and
that's because
um oh oh didn't in point wait what
happened
here uh remind me later oh I got I got
interrupted here I did I got interrupted
here let me try
again
worlds
um there we go so there we have a world
so what I'm trying to show you is that
you can use Unicode on the uh as a
thing there's going to be people out
there like what are you doing there's no
quotes Okay we're dealing with absolute
beginners they don't know what's up with
that yet all right so let's introduce
the first
type okay this is a string and I want
you to I want you to imagine with me uh
there's a problem here though right so
what's really happening here is that
this all the stuff that comes after the
command is being combined together into
a string into what's called a string now
that what's actually probably better is
this put two quotes on it now we're
going to talk about what a string is
okay um a string is a sequence of
characters
um sometimes called runes sometimes
called shs but there all you care about
is that it's a you know a thing that
shows up on the screen numbers and
letters emojis they're all included if
you really want to go down into the
weeds this all based on YouTube f8 which
is what gave us emojis and stuff like
that which was invented by Rob Pike and
Thompson who also invented go by the way
so very fun into the weeds kind of thing
there uh and we've already talked about
how terminals are really just big fancy
teletype machines that have turned you
know modern um and that's that's
important right because there's a bunch
of things happening here like what
happens if we had another one hello
world uh again right let's add another
one by the way wait how do I do that
we're going to copy that line y y and
then we're going to paste the line after
P now we're going to change it so then
we put it on the H and we do
C2 quote and that says change everything
up to the next quote double quote and we
say hello again world right okay now
let's let's commit it with with Escape
in my case control left bracket never
control C totally stupid and and then
we're going to exit that was shift ZZ
zzy top Z I'm going to sleep uh and then
we're going to run it
temp all right so then it runs both of
those lines one after the other as if
they had been executed on the command
line so far so good right I mean this is
really easy stuff but I'm going slow on
purpose um okay so let's keep going
um uh okay so we have those two things
that happen um okay so but let's let's
do the next thing okay
um I I don't know when to bring this up
let's actually go ahead and bring it up
right now because it's really fun um now
let's do variables first okay so but
what if you see how this has got hello
twice uh and in in coding we have a
thing it's called do not repeat yourself
D do D what is it do not repeat yourself
or um you know so and sometimes you have
to repeat yourself but that's the whole
point of programming with a procedure
again you would say go go do this thing
again right so right here wouldn't it be
great if we could just put this this if
we could just use that same thing both
times right so let's do that let's make
that into a thing let's say uh so we're
going to make it a variable we're going
to
say um I mean this is kind of a stupid
one uh let
say hello we'll say hello
equals hello world all right now I want
a couple things about here now it's
telling me that it's not being used Shi
check is saying hey you're not using it
you need to use it okay let's go use it
so then we're going to come down here
and we're going to do dollar sign
hello same down
here I'll change this I don't care so
whoops uh
hello again all right
so that's our first use of a variable
and let's run it and then I'm going to
talk about it all right so it runs all
right now if you want to have separate
tabs for this you can do that by the way
if you want another window to be running
it for you you can let me let me show
you a really quick trick by the way this
is kind of fun you can actually
automatically run your
program uh so you can see what it's
doing anytime the file changes so this
is kind of a bonus but let me show you
this so there's ENT command ENT you just
have to memorize this right now uh an
b-c clear semicolon and then we're going
to say um we're going to run the program
uh temp Fu in this case whatever your
program name is um and then we're going
to send it uh the name of the program
file that we're going to watch okay and
this is this is in this case it's only
one file you can do this with lots of
files we'll talk about that another day
so this is a really fun little command
and uh and now anytime there's any
change made to the program I can
actually see that now if you we haven't
done anything about how to use t-o so
you might have this in two separate tabs
if put Windows whatever I have split a
pane here because just for the sake of
convenience um and now I'm going to go
back up in my case is contrl a up Arrow
or K and I can actually change this like
I can change this to Capital H and then
when I save it it automatically runs a
program you can see the changes um you
know using nothing more than standard
tools I would use on the job so we have
hello again down here and so what we see
is we see that we have what's called a
variable hello is being assigned and now
I I have to spent some time on the equal
sign here uh I learned very much the
hard way that beginners don't understand
that the equal sign does not mean is
equal to and this it's really
unfortunate uh that you know we didn't
the world in general didn't have a
better way to say put the thing on the
right into the thing on the left it
would have been so much better if we
could have done something like that this
is not a thing please don't think it is
but if if I if I had done this instead
you know oops I mean you know it would
have been so much better if we could
have had something like an arrow or
something you know to say hey put the
thing on the right into the thing on the
left hey thank you for the raid I'm I'm
making a video so I'm just going to keep
going um anyway so um so that's what the
single equal sign in this case means the
single equal sign in this case means
take the thing on the right in this case
Hello World and put it into the box or
the variable on the left and you know if
you're really young I would talk to you
about you know having a single thing in
the box at the same time you put one
thing in I'd actually have a a visual
you can imagine having a box I used to
do this with kids like really young kids
I say okay I'm putting one thing in the
box now can I have two things in the Box
no I have to take that out because I
don't have room in there that's what
it's like you can think of hello as
being a box that you're putting a thing
in and you can put something else in it
but when you do that thing has to leave
and that is a variable if you know what
functions are so a variable means it can
change what's the difference between the
word variable and
constant constant means it never changes
variable there's no such thing as a
constant in in uh bash as far as I know
but um there are variables you can have
variables you just don't change and
those are effectively constants right so
so every language is different some of
them have more strict types some have
very loose types but in this case we
have a variable called hello and we're
putting something called a string into
it so
um yeah I know yes which has been the
source of Kernel vulnerability since C
if C equals 1 is a valid syntax but
probably isn't what you want yeah
absolutely yeah in fact in in Python
it's really really dangerous too yeah
python using a single equal sign instead
of double equal sign is really bad and
and I'll show you a sense of that later
but for right now beginners just need to
know that the equal sign means take the
thing on the right put it in put it into
the thing on the left and and then you
can reuse it and this Dollar in the case
of bash every language is different but
this language says hey this word that
follows the dollar that refers to the
box you can think of it as a label on
the box I want that to be there and it
will replace it at that spot um and I'm
avoiding a conversation about about
expansion and how you can hack Shell
Code based on that but that's for later
um
is there a read only constant keyword
did not know that today I just
learned you know what I think I did know
that but I had forgotten I I vaguely
remember
that yeah let's try that let's do this
let's say so somebody just reminded me
that there's actually a a thing so hello
equals whoops equals
other greeting let's try that see what
happens uhoh Hello read only variable
it's funny Shel didn't even catch that
that shell Che didn't even catch that
interesting read only SPX nice okay so
PX is is shell that's before bash we're
not going to talk about why bash right
now we'll get into a little bit later so
anyway so that's interesting so there
there are constants I guess I was wrong
so there's constant I've never used one
but there you go there's constants
constant means you can set it saying hey
I can never change it so that's that's
kind of cool actually we don't want that
in this case but good to know all right
so save that again and we have our
changes so again let's uh let's actually
get rid of the read only and see what
happens let's try that oh look at it
other greeting again all right so that
did what we wanted all right nice good
job d r declare d r is equ yeah okay so
we're not we're not getting into declare
right now because we're still dealing
with beginners um because we haven't
talked about types yet but we will I
promise so right now we're just talking
about variables so variables are hey I
have this thing and I want to put this
thing into this other thing so let's
talk about what this thing is hello
world what the hell is it okay this
thing here is actually a variable and
what that means is I'm sorry this is a
string so a string when every time I
would teach kids about strings I used to
have a necklace uh with beads on it so
imagine you have a beaded necklace this
is s for your head you have a beaded
necklace and on the end on the end of
the necklace you have these two knots
and the knots are the knots are the
quotes Okay and in the case of strings
in bash you can have either knots you
know different types of knots you can
have the knots that are double or single
single quotes these are specifically
these are prime but you know on an
American keyboard that is like kind of
by the return key right so you have
either a single one uh or a double one
it is not a back tick which is up by the
the number one on an American keyboard
that's not it that has a different KN
meaning and we'll get into that so
the syntax is for string is to put you
know these quotes around it and that
says Hey I want all that stuff in there
to be together if you leave one off you
can think of the beads falling off the
string and you get a syntax eror all
right so you know that's when stuff kind
of comes apart on you um now so based on
that you can actually as you can see you
can take a variable and add it into the
string you can kind of inject it into
the string and say I want this variable
to be here but the first thing you need
to know about the quotes is if I Chang
this to single
quotes then things break up right and
you see I want you to see the output so
hey thanks hi so if you see the output
down here you can see the output see
look what it did you see what it
did I don't have to say anything about
this you can just get it from what it's
what it's doing when it has double
quotes it shell interprets it and it
changes the colors and everything for
you so you can see it and it it does the
replacement for you when you have single
quotes it's like no I don't want you to
do I don't want to do any replacement at
all and that's very important right so
there's one last thing to keep in mind
here what if I have a
quote right what if what if my hello
world and I want to say like I mean if
it's single quotes that's a pretty
obvious one
right it's like if I I say like what if
I want air quotes about worlds right I
wanted to do something like that so
now it's like you see how I put the
single quotes around there but I don't
want that I want I I want it to be like
air quotes you know like World
ums most other languages do yeah so
we're just sticking with bash right now
so now what as you can Shield check's
giving me the problem it's like wait I
can't do this what the hell right and I
already told you how to look up the
errors for shield check right so it's
like go look this
up so you can't do that um
andless I can't I'm getting ahead of
myself I can't there's some really cool
situation where you can use multiple
quoted
syntaxes with when you're doing when
you're doing command and interpolation
but I'm getting ahead so watch if you do
this uh view can yeah what I'm this
that's why I'm trying that's why I pick
bash specifically one of my friends on
YouTube here is saying that this stuff
is the same for almost all languages
this is really good for them for
languages for later and that's why I
picked bash on purpose because a lot of
these concepts are are going to pass
forward with you when you learn
programming uh officially so so we put
this slash in front of the thing it's
actually a backslash and people get this
wrong all the time okay so please make
sure that right now you're writing your
notes or you in your brain your gray
matter whatever that you remember that a
backslash and a slash are not the same
thing okay this is called The Backs
slash sometimes called a back whack by
hackers there's like whack and back
whack don't say that just say
backslash so if it's a backslash that
means okay I don't really mean a quote
here I mean the actual quote thing and
and this is this idea of escaping a
single Rune or a single character or
whatever you want to call it um is
common it's common throughout all
languages as an escape uh and one of the
reasons I like bash for this is because
unlike python it doesn't muddy the
waters with this
if you're using single quotes um yeah if
you're using single quotes then you
always always get it watch what happens
when I do single quotes here this is
kind of weird watch okay did you see
what happened when you use single quotes
this is the takeaway when you use single
quotes there is no
escaping except for one thing there's
only one thing you can escape in a
single quote and that's a single quote
oh
boy or maybe not maybe I got that wrong
I was wrong I guess you can't even do
that I guess you can't there are some
languages that let you do that but not
this
one nope couldn't parse a single quote
fix it more looking back and matching
wow that's cool yeah so anyway the point
of it is that you can go back and forth
between the kind of quotes that you use
and you get the different kind of
quoting that you prefer
so that's I I totally forgot about that
I didn't realize you cannot you cannot
quote even a back
tick yeah oh you have to do the the
thing yeah yeah all right so now here's
the thing let's say there's one last
thing you can do um you can actually
join two of these things together um so
you can join two of these things
together so like if you really wanted to
have single
quotes uh I'm kind of going in the weeds
here but if you really wanted single
quotes you could do this you could do
that and then you can put another string
right away that's got that's got single
quotes world and then you could have
that now I want you to think about what
that's doing this is uniquely bash by
the way so bash as long as it comes
right after it as long as it immediately
after it it joins the two things
together um so this is this is actually
the same in in other languages you would
write this like this so it obviously
that's not a thing but it's like take
this string and then add it to this
other string right but but in bash you
can just write them right next to each
other and you get that equivalent if you
put a space here it'll actually not do
it so this is uniquely bash but that is
a regularly people regularly use that
technique uh to to do that kind of thing
um and if you can pause this video and
keep replaying it and you understand
what just happened there you can say
that you have you know you now
understand shell expansion um and you
know the basics of quotes and stuff like
that uh now it goes without saying that
you can't say
this why was like can I just do that no
you can't why because it doesn't know
what it
is right it it's it's it's giving you a
really really weird uh error here
because what it's doing is it's it's
assigning this variable and then it's
trying to run a command it's trying to
run world as a command now the takeaway
from that is Thou shalt always put
quotes around your
strings okay and you saw me not do that
a couple times but that's the reason you
should do it so we're going to do that
we're going to say since we we since we
know there's no going to be variables in
here we're going to do single quotes
because they're easier to type to I'm
actually
a a fan of single quotes whenever
possible just because they're easier to
type and they're easier to read frankly
in my opinion but you do you do you you
do whatever you want um so anyway there
we go there's there's we we've covered
variables we've covered the echo command
uh while we're on the echo command let's
actually talk about one other command
it's called print and it is the same as
Echo um
except I'm going to go print F uh it's
the same as Echo but instead of this it
uses these really cool things called
placeholders and we can put a hello here
instead and then we can use this we can
say uh percent uh I think it's s Right
double quote to prevent globbing okay so
you see this this is shell check saving
your life and I'm not going to tell you
what this error is but if you don't do
this then somebody can hack you if the
information that's going into these
variables comes outside they could put a
little shell script inside of that
variable and run it
instead of having it do what you want so
when shell tells you to quote something
to prevent word splitting that's what
it's doing it's saving you from you know
potential bugs later and believe me if
you're a hacker looking for this kind of
bugs is is a good thing you can find
that a lot right so um yeah and yeah so
so there we go
um yeah there we go so so now we have
now this this thing is interesting so
printf what does it do it takes a single
string with these special place markers
in it and then it puts a space and then
it has this other thing that's got a
variable but it's almost its own string
right and we can actually do something
else we could say uh whatever because we
don't need to escape that but if we had
if we had another one here now we can
say hello again whatever and you can see
it puts it in the right place now
there's a bunch of advanced things with
print up that we can do that we can't do
with Echo such as give it some padding
right so I can print hello whatever I
can put uh other you know and oops uh oh
look at that it didn't put a line return
Echo does print doesn't so we're going
to put something the first time this is
your first escape and this is what's
called A Line Feed remember I told you
about teletype this is a line feed this
says Advance the terminal one thing and
as you can see it actually shows you
down below that it lines them up pretty
well right so those are two commands you
can put in your notes uh to get us going
and we're almost off to that we did it
in 35 minutes the rest of the stuff is
pretty easy we're going to do flow
control and functions and math and we're
going to be done okay so this is the
basic thing understanding how to print
stuff out is really really important um
we're not going to write to files in
this video that's going to be another
video all by itself so um so right now
we're just printing all this out as you
can see if you put a you put a I think a
dash here it makes it go the other
direction uh I don't know why you would
do that but you know you could do that
um and there's a lot of other things
that you can put here
so um you know those are those are all
going to help you make nice pretty
things that that you know show up uh
whether you use echo or not is a thing
something important about Echo is that
Echo does not allow you to use escapes
there are versions of echo that let you
put d e in here and so that you can do
that but in general you should not do
that in general in my opinion you should
either use echo or print F because not
all versions of echo allow you to do
that so if you want to be precise about
your escapes and put multiple lineary
returns in a thing you can use print out
for that um you'll see this a lot you'll
see people with like 25 Echo statements
one for each individual line where they
could have done it like this um
something else about uh line returns
here let's try this so hello
again here is a
thing all right so we're going to save
that and you see how it kept all the
line returns right so you you cannot do
if you wanted to do that kind of thing
you could do you could change it to be
printf and you could do this you could
say and then join those back again you
know put Dash error uh you know if if if
you want it just depends on what you
want how how how you want to process it
and stuff so
uh oh
wait this is kind of hard uh a thing
okay so print up here is a
thing all right so that does the same
you see it prints the same right so that
is that's the thing uh the one other
thing I want to show you is well I don't
know if we should show you this um
there's something called here strings so
if you if you want a string that's
really long you can say I I didn't want
to do this but we're going to do it
anyway so you could say uh you know a
story equals and you could say this um
no I'm not doing it I'm not doing here
I'm not doing here her dos yet we're not
doing her dos until we have file and
Direction then we'll do that I get ahead
of myself can you print it for a
variable instead of set
out uh you cannot print up to a variable
no uh there there is we're getting ahead
of ourselves but the answer to your
question is
um wait where is story oh that's not
happy it's still okay anyway so uh
somebody asked if they can actually
print a variable and have it uh show up
in a variable using sprintf uh is there
a sprintf there's no such thing as that
if I wanted this to go into a variable
how would I do it you do it like
this yeah and they you say another we
haven't done this yet but I wanted to to
show you this and now we can say
Echo uh
another and and it'll it'll do it double
quoting right what's double
quote so so there that's that's what you
can do this is this we haven't done this
yet but we're going to we're going to
definitely cover this what this does is
this puts a little teeny program inside
of another program it's called a
subshell or subprocess and it runs the
program takes the output of the program
and then assigns
that right and that's a very common
technique uh in shell and that is
actually extremely uh a extremely
powerful part of showell programming
which you'll see a lot of lately when we
get on to it later I'm kind of ahead of
myself on that but that you're going to
see a lot of that and shell um doing
that kind of thing with a more serious
language is kind of a no no because why
you could just do the thing um but that
that is the equivalent of of that and so
but it is kind of fun to see that early
on because that is one of the advantages
of show right is that anything becomes
its own you know command its own script
its own thing and you can actually take
the output of one thing and put it into
another thing or pipe it into another
thing all kinds of stuff um there are
ways to uh to take um you know strings
and use them as files but we haven't got
on to that yet okay back to what I was
uh just doing so let me go back all
right so we've covered we've covered
variables we've covered we've covered
print we've covered escaping and now
it's time to like let's talk about like
logic flow okay so this is where we have
to I'm gonna we're not going to do
interactivity we're going to do that
next time so next time we're going to do
do interactivity yes we covered strings
and strings so but now what if we did
this we could say uh let's say Lang
equals
French all right so we could have two
words here we could have uh Sal I mean
this I'm totally contrived but we say uh
salour
bour
Leon they SP that right s isn't getting
used Lang isn't getting used and let's
just to shut it up let's actually shut
it up for a second I'm going to comment
it out so it doesn't yell at me tell I'm
using it okay so Echo hello so we don't
want to to say let's get rid of these
echool and everything again um in fact
let's uh which one should we keep let's
just keep this basic one for now all
right so what if we said I when a
language we want to say when the
language is French uh I want to say
something different okay so this is the
first uh branching condition or flow and
Bas that's a lot of words in there but
it's just basically if this then do this
all right so in procedural programming
it's usually if this then that and
there's actually another element of
procedural programming you can
incorporate called event-based
programming and the difference between
procedural programming and event
programming anybody want to name a
really common event based language
JavaScript right event programming it's
a different Paradigm and it's when this
do this these are both instructions you
could give to you know an employee or a
military or anything it's like when this
then do this so when the conditions are
like this then do this thing and now if
then is the difference between when then
and if then is that when then implies
that there's some sort of like continual
monitoring of the situation to see if
the state has changed if the environment
has changed if something about the
environment has changed when you notice
something new then do this right we're
going to get in there later I just want
to give you an overview of of flow
because one of the flows is still linear
and the one then is is got an implied
flow that there's a loop around the
whole thing can you guess what A bash
interpreter is
doing a bash interpreter reppel is an
infinite loop it's constantly infinite
looping we're going to get there later
in a second but I'm kind of get ahead
myself but I want you when we do if then
we're still linear right beginning step
step step step now we're done but we're
going to put a thing around it later and
hopefully we'll get to that today in
fact we got 15 minutes so we should make
it okay so so right now let's do the
condition if the language I mean let's
just write out what we would write out
in English Okay we would say something
like this if the language is French uh
then do this and this is not a thing
this is not a thing so we'll put a
comment and say then do this uh uh
otherwise uh yeah otherwise we'll do
this I didn't spell that right well I
got to fix it all right otherwise do
that all right
so right so we could say if the language
is French then we want this to be
Salo but there isn't a Salo let's go
uncomment
it okay so otherwise do this now you can
see it's printing both of them out right
now why it's printing both of them out
right now it's printing both of them out
because because
why oopsie
Sorry God come on Rob come on Rob be
better be
best all right so um it's doing both of
them why well we haven't added the code
here so the this is the English that you
would write but the bash is not too far
from that so we would say if right we
can
test we want to test something so we
want to
test if I mean this isn't going to work
but I want to show you this anyway if we
want to test if the language if the
Lang
equals
right uh
French then and we put a semicolon there
right could parse this expression fixed
to allow more BL all right so that's
kind of what we want to write but we
can't write that there's actually a
command that will test for that but
instead of writing test here we're going
to actually use two double brackets and
some posic person just lost their mind
on me when I wrote that I don't care I'm
going to tell you why that's the right
way to write this um so it says so
instead of having we're just going to
use a single equal sign here uh could PR
fix to allow
more wait what what am I doing wrong
here I've got a mistaken
here oh right um
oh wait we don't have a f in there okay
we have to replace this some otherwi all
right so anytime you have an if
statement you need to put a five to end
the thing okay so and then otherwise is
the word else okay now when I save this
it's going to automatically restructure
for me sh fmt did that that's why I told
you to get it so because then I don't
want to screw around with spacing and
crap I just want it to work so so there
we go
uh yeah okay so here we
go
um second repeats I don't know what that
why it's doing that my video doesn't do
that uh do you think it's possible to
make simple recip no no and why would
you it's completely
stupid um so if language reference but
not a sign Okay so Lang is up here but
there is no Lang because it's still
commented out so let's define it up
here all right I I want to show you
something though that's very very
important about bash and this anybody
who's coded in another language will not
know this um what happens if I add a
space
here it dies right because bash is very
specific shell any shell programming
language they very very very
specifically do not allow spaces there
because they arguments separate AR
actually so it's very important that you
understand that you have to have no
spaces uh around your equal sign when
you're doing assignment when you're
taking the thing on the right putting a
thing in the left so there we go all
right so now we have B we only have one
output and what if we change the
language to be
Russian all right it's still saying
hello world
right so it could say French all right
and it's
saying right okay so we're going to do
another thing that's not as common but
so there's our conditional flow right
it's like if I have this thing I'm going
to do this and I that a break in the
flow and now we have one other thing
let's actually say uh Prat which I I'm
just going to write in English because
I'm doing the thing see you um okay so
let's say
private I guys uh I could write this in
Russian I'm not going
to so I'm just going to write per uh
Leon it should be it should instead of
should be uh I
mean I don't know should we say should
we say or should just say PR PR's fine
it's it's less formal but who cares so
priv
lont let's do PR PR uh
all right
SOA Mundo yeah we could have Ola Ola
Mundo Ola Mundo I love it all right so
we got a lot of names here yada yada
yada right so okay and I'm probably this
probably not the best logic but you're
going to see this is on purpose so right
now it says French right so no matter
what other language it is there's
another how do we add another language
all right well do I could just add else
again
right uh if if you have continuous un
empty characters that's correct Dale yes
if it's a simple thing you don't really
need it but it's you can do it just as a
matter of of thing but Shel Che doesn't
care so I don't do it I don't do
anything I don't have
to so Echo
um Pim is that you
[Music]
okay some somebody in my twitch just
realized I speak Russian and they didn't
know
that that I lived there for
years okay so what else
um and and I I can
actually yeah I can type it if I want
but I forgot anyway so anyway let's do
so Echo you can see there's problems
here though it's
like right this is the worst program
ever but it's making the point so Echo
what Echo else what well we need to add
another condition okay so there's other
thing called LF and that gives us allow
another condition we can say Lang equals
um uh Spanish how about
that
Spanish then all right and it's it's
that anytime it does that to you and
you're not ready to write something just
put a call in it's called the null
operator and that'll like shut up shell
check for a bit if you want to do that
but but we know what to put here we can
say
Echo you
know Sal can anybody see a better way to
write this already I bet you can think
of it
I bet you
can I bet you can think of a better way
to write
this P appears unused okay we'll comment
it out for
now and let's actually make
it L Lang equals Uh
Russian then
all right now let's do
it okay so now we get Bon Leon we get
French we can change this to Russian we
get
oops we get
privat if we change it
to
Spanish we get Olam Mundo now do you see
already some there's a couple of things
we can do here
okay so uh we're almost out of time on
this we're probably going have to wait
and do loops next well we could probably
do loops and functions next actually
let's just make this a longer video
because I want to get it all into one
all right so this looks kind of messy
right I mean there's so many things we
could do better here so but that's how a
beginner would write it a beginner would
write it by just using IF then they if
then then this if it's this or if it's
this or if it's this or if it's this
that's the flow that's the logic that's
the flow and um
but there are better ways to do that and
so I'm going to introduce you to
something that python doesn't have and
this is one of the reasons I hate
teaching python to beginners so I'm
going to teach you to another uh way of
doing this it's something called a case
or a switch block and it's akin to in
real world of saying something like in
case you have this then do this or this
or this or this right and it's actually
called the case so
I'm going to jump in and show it to you
right
away uh my mar actually yes don't you
love it yeah and YouTube is like yes
please bring on the case so case is case
is very unique and it's a unique case
and what it says is I want to take
whatever is in there the Lang in this
case
right and then is it do or done I can't
remember and then esack and by the way
way the first language to do that was
algo the first language ever to like
reverse its things like that was
algo okay and let's see I think is it
case I I'm my case name is I don't
remember it's case or
switch what am I missing oh no it's
case I I am totally spacing my case
statements I don't I have to go look at
couldn't is saying more checks oh in of
course yeah I don't use case every day
but I love them there we go case in yeah
all right so anyway so case the language
is in blah blah blah right now the
reason Shel Che didn't yell at me for
not quoting that is because it's a
single word Spanish
here and now it will probably yell at me
nope didn't okay good all right well
there you go good to know I I've noticed
that bash is just so much sh Che get so
much less mad about so much it's kind of
cool I love
it all right
so all right we only have one hello
world so let's get that all right so how
can we change what we just had so the
first thing by the way you see
else so so let's let's talk about this
this is a very specific thing
um
so the here we get into to deal with
like expansions it's called glob
expansion and now we get into some of
the advantages of a of a of an
interpreted language or any kind of
language because we can use some of
these constructs to make our life easier
so in this case the star what does the
star mean the star means anything it's
sometimes called a Splat or a glob uh
glob star whatever it means anything
that means whatever is in laying
whatever's in
there if it's literally anything then do
this and these two semicolons that is a
way of ending the line and and that's
just syntax that's just something you
have to remember and so what we're going
to put here is um we're going to do this
one right so we're going to say
Echo and put a space there it's
generally wise to put spaces in in Shell
actually I yeah well
I need I need my world again where's my
world all right so here's my world my
terminal West term is pretty good at at
showing you these emojis because they
take up two character slots all right so
we're actually printing out two things
now let's actually comment all of this
out I'm going to show you a trick that
you're going to learn how to do later uh
I'm going to do exclamation point
a uh F no exclamation point AP
that says send the entire paragraph that
I'm in uh to the following command the
command is CMT and that's going to
automatically comment all those lines I
am not going to use visual mode for that
I'm going to use my CMT and in case you
want to see what's in the CMT
command here it is that's it it just
Loops through the things and adds a
thing into the front of the line and
that's what we're going to learn how to
do that's why we're learning how to to
code in bash so let's go back to our
code so here we go we have all these
variables that are no longer being used
well let's fix
that okay so let's do that so you can
probably guess I'm copying this line
it's like we can't have two of the same
so we have to change one of them so
let's say if this one is
Russian then let's Echo
preate all right there one of our
explanation points one away now you can
probably guess the rest of them right so
French uh salute
and
Spanish is
Ola all right all of our things are done
and now it's doing exactly the same
thing take a screenshot of that because
which one is easier to
read
right all right and that is the only
purpose of this is is that and you can
actually put if you want to you can put
some wi space here in fact in this
particular
case um
oops uh so in this particular case you
probably would want to put some white
space here just so it's easier to read
right if you do go with the if
statements you probably don't want them
all crammed into a thing Whit space is
fine but we don't need it
anymore uh you can write more than one
line in a case yes you absolutely can
you just use single uh you use you can
either do
this um in fact some people do this
this is what some people
prefer um and you could have Echo uh uh
Ola
again right and you can have and these
as long as you put them on their own
line you don't need to have the the
thing in there right so you can do that
now if you if you want it to be easier
to read you can write it like this of
course if you're putting too much of
that in there you probably should start
thinking about a function which we're
going to get to
so um so it is it's the main takeaway
from this right now is it's just an easy
way to uh make you know stuff like that
now you can do a lot of magic with this
right so the first magic I want to show
you so so first of all this right here
don't need it we don't need it anymore
we can write this now instead all right
so the difference is that now we
have this right well since the we're
pretty re what I want to show you is you
only need this you can say in fact we
don't even need the whole thing because
there's no repetition we could do this
and it'll be
fine now that I'm doing that for a
reason
because you can use this technique to do
some pretty magical things in posic
Shell um when you're trying to decide
whether something has you know something
inside of it or not I'm getting ahead of
myself but later on you'll see that
that's very valuable we are not going to
get into all the different forms of uh
globstar expansion uh that you can put
in here but what this is is it's like
anything in fact if I wanted to I could
say anything that has Lut in it we're
going to have that match wait that's
that's Russian sorry what was this one s
Spanish
so oh we can say Anish any any Ani all
right
so bu is one word yes it is thank you
thank you for the reminder bu um so the
point is this I want you to see okay and
you can also use one last thing you can
use individual question marks for like I
just want one letter here versus the
okay so that's globstar expansion in
like a nutshell the the Splat means any
amount of thing and the the the question
mark means one random
thing that's it for now I don't want to
blow you away right there's lots more to
come but that's the beginning okay
so um so yeah so anyway there you go so
this means anything and by the way this
is sequential right so if none of these
match then this one hits and if one of
them matches does it still do the next
one that's a good question let's try it
so what if we did this let's do
uh let's do s star so that's for
Spanish right but what if we wanted to
say if it's Spanish or
French right so let's keep them out here
or
French all right and I'm going to
comment that out for
now so Sal onuse so so now I can have
two things I can have Spanish or
French all right and this this this
particular this is this is a wonderful
rabbit hole that just keeps on going so
but learning case is a really important
um way of doing that is it easy to read
not as much as if saavs maybe I don't
know it just depends on you but it gives
you a lot of power and you can have
multiple things here it's extremely
powerful so you know just know the the
the the free form
uh nature of it is is is what allows
that to match that okay so I am going to
resist the temptation to show you about
equality in conditions for now
um because reasons but but I do want to
show you this thing first so
um okay so you see how much easier this
is to write than the other
ones uh and it will continue P matching
but if you wish to do the next one
changed to blah blah oh I didn't know
about that I didn't know about that you
can do this that's the
thing I've never use that in my entire
life thank you for telling me about that
that's cool so if you wanted to continue
if you wanted to Des send down you can
apparently you can put it in erson after
that I've never used that though so
that's the end of that we're we're we're
getting stuck in the weeds here so let's
keep going so let's keep it back up on
the high level I I love getting into the
weeds it's so easy to get into the weeds
with with with bash because it's so much
fun it's got so much power in it uh yeah
r RC has better syntax than bash bash is
the standard Linux shell why would you
suggest anybody learn anything but that
yeah I'm teaching people to be
productive on any system that's got bash
installed which is tens of millions if
not billions of systems how many
machines are is RC install on yeah
thought so I I hate it when people
recommend [__] that is on their computer
because they installed it on there it's
completely us waste of time so anyway
let me keep going so you got this you
got this you get the point here okay but
let's actually do one last thing in
refactoring on this code and we'll move
on um
so yeah anyway
so all right obviously this is redundant
right we have this we have this this
world every time the only thing that's
really changing is this thing in the
front here right well what if we made
that a
variable what if we made that a variable
instead can you guys think about what
you would do here all right so I want
you to stop the video right now because
you have everything in your power this
is the exercise part
okay right now everything that we have
just covered I'm going to give you a
challenge and then I'm going to do it
right away
right now you have been given all the
tools necessary to refactor this code in
a way that makes it easier to rather
than having all these variables it only
has one
variable okay and you're going to be
using what you know and you're going to
be able to assign a variable into
another variable you're going to be able
to assign something into other variabl
So based on all the information you now
know
write a a refactor refactor this script
so that the end result is that there's
only one Echo statement down here
there's just one Echo statement and it
says something here I'm not going to
tell you what it is and then it has your
world Emoji
okay all right stop the video and make
that and now I'm going to tell you the
answer
okay um it's you know it's not it's not
that hard but but I wanted you to take a
take a moment to like process everything
you've just learned why isn't that doing
that that's kind of annoying me I'm
gonna have to steal one of these my
emoji is not not happy for some
reason uh all right so like
this okay so how would you do it how
would you do
it
um yeah uh I mean YouTuber just joined
us no idea what we're doing it's always
fun all right so we want it you're we
want it so that this this code is going
to have to change so I'm going to put
this here to do uh
change uh
refactor so only one
Echo okay there you go that is that is
the the challenge okay here's the answer
get ready pause the video If you're not
ready if you're not ready pause the
video here's the answer so the next
thing we're going to
do is we're going to go ahead and and do
this uh then bash is excellent
yes um I'm glad you
approve it's s like I've been doing it
for two
decades um so we get trolls on YouTube
as usual um giving me you know back
seating how I teach people
yeah yeah it's Paradise YouTube is
Paradise all right so here we go re
refactor City Line so did you get your
answer already all right here's the
answer okay I'm going to go ahead and do
it so don't watch this until you're
ready all right we the the solution is
this we don't need to repeat this every
time there's only one thing that needs
to change here right so instead of
having this do this we can change this
and we can say I want we need another
variable right here right what is this
variable going to be let's make one
we'll call it uh greeting all right so
greeting there's no greeting yet we
don't we haven't defined it so let's say
uh
that the greeting if it if they're
Spanish then the greeting
equals
Ola all right now and then if it's this
and it's it's not much less code but it
you
know greeting equals
Salo but the challenge was was kind of
for a purpose
so you have it just be greed
instead but you get the point and then
um so greeting equals
hello and in fact if you wanted to do
that you could actually you don't even
need this here you could actually Define
it up here and you could say you could
have the grading be the default you
could say
greeing equals
um you know hello by
default all right so that's that's our
defaults if you do that you can get rid
of this one down
here and that's you know this will not
happen unless unless the other one has
been been a thing right so um now
actually uh hello equals Hello
World um
well let's do this greeting equals H
we'll say it like
that so we'll say the default is is H so
B so now we can change French we can say
I want it to be
Spanish and then we get olon we change
it to what is it
Russian and we get prad Mir we change it
to French and you get you get the point
of this is that this is exactly what we
mean by variable we can vary what this
value is so that it changes the behavior
so we vary the state of the program how
it runs based on changing its
instructions changing its parameters and
I'm using these words on purpose because
we're going to use those words next so
my wife is gone for right now so I'm
going to go ahead and make another video
I'm going to do another hourong video
and we're going to move into the next
phase of this and we're going to
introduce um you know the other phase of
of procedural programming a little bit
more conditional programming and and go
from there um all right so so there we
go that this has been variables this has
been basic conditions and flow and
including the case statement so I'm
going to T pause the video and take a
break and I'm come back I'm going to
make another video and we'll proceed
with another holiday Boost video uh and
we'll keep going with bash we'll see how
many we can get in tonight before my
wife gets back
okay